Dr Josh Veitch-Michaelis

I am computer vision engineer with cross-domain expertise and over a decade of software development experience. I have worked in academia and industry, from space science to ecology and I'm passionate about using technology for social good. In my spare time I enjoy the satisfaction of making things - from woodwork to electronics to brewing. I boulder regularly, play the piano and am a solo glider pilot.

Experience

Feb 2022- ETH Zürich / Restor Eco

Zürich, Switzerland

Postdoc in AI for Remote Sensing

• Developing machine learning algorithms for forest conservation

Aug 2020–Dec 2021 Wisconsin-Madison University

South Pole, Antarctica

IceCube Winterover Experiments Operator

 Operate and maintain the IceCube Neutrino Observatory at the South Pole, providing critical hardware and software support (on-call 24/7 year-round).

Jun 2018–Jun 2020 Liverpool John Moores University

Liverpool, UK

Postdoctoral Research Assistant in Drone Image Analyses (Astro-Ecology)

- Led instrument design for a real-time, drone-mounted endangered species. detection system using thermal/visible imaging and deep learning.
- Collaborations with Save The Elephants (Kenya), WWF, ZSL (London), Durrell (Madagascar) and Knowsley Safari.
- Development of an automatic spectral calibration pipeline for the 2m Liverpool Tele-

Jun 2019-Aug 2019 Frontier Development Lab, Europe

Oxford, UK; ESRIN, Italy

Researcher

- Worked on a team developing a flood segmentation algorithm for deployment on a satellite, supported by UNICEF and the European Space Agency (ESA). Selected from over 400 applicants.
- Research presented orally at Humanitarian Aid and Disaster Response workshop at NeurIPS 2019 (hadr.ai).
- Launched on a D-Orbit satellite in June 2021 and is currently being flight-tested in space.

Dec 2017-Jun 2018 I3D Robotics Ltd.

Tonbridge, UK

Computer vision/robotics engineer

- Designed bespoke 3D imaging systems; stereo, LIDAR, laser triangulation, high-speed image processing tools (> 400 fps).
- Led a successful InnovateUK-funded project for smart agriculture: an embedded system for deep learning-based fruit detection in greenhouses.
- Clients included robotics, heavy industry (steel), agriculture and nuclear.

Sep 2013–Dec 2017 IS Instruments Ltd.

Tonbridge, UK

Photonics engineer, STFC-CASE (industrial) PhD student

• Led end-to-end design of a commercial IoT miniature spectrometer. This involved obtaining grant funding, PCB design and embedded firmware (Atmel AVR), optomechanical design and end-user software development.

Education

2012-2016	PhD in Space and Climate Physics	Mullard Space Science Lab, University College London
	Fusion of LIDAR with stereo camera data -	an assessment

- Remote Sensing and Photogrammetry Society award for best thesis 2017.
- STFC-CASE industrial studentship. Supervisors: Prof Jan-Peter Muller (UCL), Dr David Walton (UCL) and Dr Jonathan Storey (IS-Instruments Ltd.).
- Explored industrial applications of 3D imaging techniques used in space science.
- Optimised and parallelised stereo matching algorithms for planetary terrain reconstruction. Supervised machine learning to predict stereo matching performance; crack segmentation in cast steel.

2008–2012 BSc MPhys in Physics, first class honours

Systematics of Quark masses and mixings, supervised by Prof. Paul Harrison.

University of Warwick

Technical Skills

programming:

- Python, C++, Qt (GUI development), shell
- Data science and machine learning tools (numpy, scikit-learn, pytorch), deployment onto edge devices
- Computer vision/robotics, OpenCV (contributor), ROS
- Linux system administration, Git, Cloud (GCP), Docker

hardware: Camera/LIDAR systems, CAD (SolidWorks), rapid prototyping (3D Printing), multi-layer PCB design (EA-GLE), digital electronics and firmware (Atmel AVR, ARM), use of standard lab test equipment

Awards

2021	Antarctica Service Medal (Winterover) Natio	nal Science Foundation, USA	
2019	Google Cloud Research Credit \$5k to support research into RGB-Thermal data fusion for ecology	LJMU	
2018	Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Systems Hackathon, 3rd Project: Automated Periodogram Selection using Machine Learning	place	
2017	Remote Sensing and Photogrammetry Society (RSPSOC) award fo	r best PhD thesis	
2016	SIM Scholar, Worshipful Company of Scientific Instrument Makers Postgraduate award for excellence in instrumentation research, nomin	UCL nated by UCL.	
2011	Undergraduate Research Scholarship Calibrating the ULTRACAM High-Speed CCD Camera	Warwick	

Outreach

2018–2019	Vice President, International Workshop for Astronomy IWA is a non-profit organisation that runs the International Astronomical Youth Camp (iayc.org). Supervised around 50 students since 2011 covering a variety of topics from photometry, exoplanets, remote sensing, electronics and robotics.
2016-Now	Webmaster, International Workshop for Astronomy Linux server administration, deployment on GCP.

Selected Publications

I am a scientific editor for the Royal Astronomical Society's Techniques and Instruments (RAS T&I) journal. † implies equal contribution. More publications may be found on my Google Scholar profile.

Towards global flood mapping onboard low cost satellites with machine learning

Gonzalo Mateo-Garcia[†], **Josh Veitch-Michaelis[†]**, Lewis Smith, Silviu Oprea, Guy Schumann, Yarin Gal, Atılım Güneş Baydin, and Dietmar Backes

Scientific Reports 11.7429 (2021)

Assessing the influence of one astronomy camp over 50 years

Hannah Dalgleish and Josh Veitch-Michaelis

Nature Astron. 3 (2019)

Massive stereo-based DTM production for Mars on cloud computers

Yu Tao, Jan-Peter Muller, Panos Sidiropoulos, Si-Ting Xiong, ARD Putri, SHG Walter, **Josh Veitch-Michaelis**, and Vladimir Yershov Planetary and Space Science 154 (2018)

Flood Detection On Low Cost Orbital Hardware

Gonzalo Mateo-Garcia[†], Silviu Oprea[†], Lewis Smith[†], **Josh Veitch-Michaelis[†]**, Atılım Güneş Baydin, Dietmar Backes, Yarin Gal, and Guy Schumann

Artificial Intelligence for Humanitarian Assistance and Disaster Response Workshop at NeurIPS, 2019

Saving Endangered Animals with Astro-Ecology

Paul Ross McWhirter and Josh Veitch-Michaelis

Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Systems XXVII, 2019

RASCAL: Towards automated spectral wavelength calibration

Josh Veitch-Michaelis and Marco Lam

Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Systems XXVIII, 2020

The International Astronomical Youth Camp: Lessons Learned in 50 Years

Hannah Dalgleish and Josh Veitch-Michaelis

Communicating Astronomy with the Public Conference 2018 2nd Edition, 2018

Enhancement of stereo imagery by artificial texture projection generated using a LIDAR

Josh Veitch-Michaelis, Jan-Peter Muller, David Walton, Jonathan Storey, Michael Foster, and Benjamin Crutchley International Archives of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences, 2016

Crack Detection in "As-Cast" Steel Using Laser Triangulation and Machine Learning

Josh Veitch-Michaelis, Yu Tao, Dave Walton, Jan-Peter Muller, Benjamin Crutchley, Jonathan Storey, Christopher Paterson, and Andrew Chown

13th Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV), 2016

An Optimised System for Generating Multi-Resolution DTMs using NASA MRO Datasets

Yu Tao, Jan-Peter Muller, Panos Sidiropoulos, **Josh Veitch-Michaelis**, and Vladimir Yershov

International Archives of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing & Spatial Information Sciences, 2016